Guide to the McNamara Defense Committee Records TAM.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McNamara Defense Committee Records
1911
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McNamara Defense Committee
TAM.033
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
A New York based committee formed in 1911 to rally support for John J. and James B. McNamara prior to their confessing to dynamiting the Los Angeles Times Building in 1910. The records contain minutes, appeals for support from labor and socialist groups, responses from these groups and financial records with lists of organizations making contributions. Much of the correspondence is that of the Committee's secretary, Socialist Party activist Julius Gerber. Included are also two letters from Samuel Gompers, and two from John J. McNamara.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Rand School Archives, 1963. There is no earlier provenance information. The accession number associated with this collection is 1963.020.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
A New York based committee formed in 1911 to rally support for John J. and James B. McNamara prior to their confessing to dynamiting the Los Angeles Times Building in 1910. The McNamara brothers were members of the International Association of Bridge and Structural Iron Workers, which was engaged in a lengthy and violent strike. Harrison Gray Otis, publisher of the Los Angeles Times, led the local business community's opposition to the local labor movement.
Scope and Content Note
The records contain minutes of committee meetings, appeals for support from labor and socialist groups, responses from these groups usually including naming of delegates to conference, and committee financial records with lists of organizations contributing. Much correspondence is that of the Committee's secretary, Socialist Party activist Julius Gerber. Two letters from Samuel Gompers support Committee efforts, and two from John J. McNamara thank Ernest Bohen for support.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Records, 1911
Labor movement |z California |z Los Angeles.; Correspondence.; Financial records; Minutes (administrative records); Bombings |z California |z Los Angeles |x History |y 20th century.; Anarchism -- United States.; Anarchists |z United States.; McNamara, John Joseph.; Los Angeles Times (Firm); McNamara Defense Committee; Bohen, Ernest; Gerber, Julius, 1862-1916; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924.; McNamara, James
- Series I: Records, 1911.
  - Agitation Fund, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Attendance Sheets and Minutes, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence about Defense Fund, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence about the McNamara Conference (I), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence about the McNamara Conference (II), 1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Defense Fund: Finances, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gompers, Samuel: Letters, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - McNamara, John J.: Telegram and Letter, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Organization and Meeting Announcements, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Page of Photographs on Los Angeles and Indianapolis Bombings: New York Times, December 17, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Receipts, Bills, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Statements of Support, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 12)